<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Fernando Correia's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-10T08:40:08-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fernando Correia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fernandoacorreia@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I should pay more attention to Dojo Toolkit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/08/10/i-should-pay-more-attention-to-dojo-toolkit/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-10T08:01:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/08/10/i-should-pay-more-attention-to-dojo-toolkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been doing a lot of research on JavaScript frameworks for developing rich client-side line-of-business applications.
So far Sencha&#8217;s <a href="http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs/">ExtJS</a> is the one I prefer for heavy-duty projects. But I&#8217;m constantly
looking around for alternatives and, more recently, <a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> caught my attention as a great choice
for structuring web apps.</p>

<p>Browser application technology is blooming and, recently, Steven Sanderson wrote an
<a href="http://blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/08/01/rich-javascript-applications-the-seven-frameworks-throne-of-js-2012/">excellent review</a> comparing several frameworks. There was a remarkable absence, though, as one commenter said:</p>

<blockquote><p>What happened to Dojo? It advocated lot of these principles years back. Was it ahead of time?</p><footer><strong>Geeth</strong> <cite><a href='http://blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/08/01/rich-javascript-applications-the-seven-frameworks-throne-of-js-2012/#comment-23446'>blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote>




<!-- more -->


<p>It&#8217;s been many years since I last thought about Dojo. In my mind it seemed to have fallen by the wayside. But that comment
picked my interest, so I went up and updated myself on the current state of Dojo affairs.</p>

<p>I found out that not only Dojo pioneered many of the techniques being applied today in several frameworks, but it has also evolved
considerably. For instance, version 1.7 introduced an improved module system, and version 1.8 modernizes the MVC structure, among a plethora of other improvements that benefit rich client applications.</p>

<p>Dojo seems to be very mature, complete and up-to-date. It has a steeper learning curve than other, smaller approaches, though,
and historically documentation and guidance for newcomers has been lacking. By the way, this is being actively worked on as well.</p>

<p>David Walsh wrote a <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/10-reasons-why-your-projects-should-use-the-dojo-toolkit/">very interesting article</a> on what Dojo has going for it. I recommend reading it if your&#8217;re interested
in JavaScript frameworks, specially for larger applications.</p>

<p>For now, I&#8217;ve decided to invest some time in learning Dojo and I&#8217;ll be sharing my experience as I go.</p>

<blockquote><p>Don’t start you next project without checking out all of the features Dojo has to offer!</p><footer><strong>David Walsh</strong> <cite><a href='http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/10-reasons-why-your-projects-should-use-the-dojo-toolkit/'>10 Reasons Why Your Projects Should Use the Dojo Toolkit</a></cite></footer></blockquote>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The impact of organizational model in innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/30/the-impact-of-organizational-model-in-innovation/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-30T12:22:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/30/the-impact-of-organizational-model-in-innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout my career I&#8217;ve been part of several innovation projects focused on applying emerging technologies to bring
new or improved products to the market. One recent example, still ongoing, is leveraging cloud computing to develop
cost-effective software-as-a-service offerings for the SMB (small and medium businesses) market segment.</p>

<p>The business management software is undergoing a deep change from monolithic, massive products that enforce rigid
business processes and are sold for costly up-front licensing fees towards more specialized, streamlined and flexible
solutions offered as a service and billed according to usage.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>David Yarnold speaks of this trend:</p>

<blockquote><p>SAP’s walls are beginning to crumble, their armor is getting weak and cloud-based enterprise applications are no longer just for small businesses.</p><footer><strong>David Yarnold</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.forbes.com/sites/ciocentral/2011/10/24/for-enterprise-it-time-to-move-beyond-sap/'>For Enterprise IT, Time to Move Beyond SAP</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>While small startups and more established new companies such as Workday and Salesforce.com are quickly innovating and
increasing their market share from the bottom up, traditional companies are slower, sometimes rehashing their
legacy products and offering them as hosted services.</p>

<p>One of the reasons is that incumbent companies are optimized for catering to their existing customer base and for
sustainable innovation, while disruptive innovation requires a different mindset and orientation.</p>

<blockquote><p>Established companies have the resources — the engineers, money, and technology — required to succeed at both sustaining and disruptive technologies. But their processes and values constitute disabilities in their efforts to succeed at disruptive innovation.</p><footer><strong>Clayton M. Christensen and Michael E. Raynor</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.amazon.com/The-Innovators-Solution-Sustaining-Successful/dp/1578518520'>The Innovator&#8217;s Solution</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>So the lesson I take is that, at this point, business management software companies need to apply distinct processes and values
to their disruptive innovation projects, or face being disrupted themselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static websites are more resilient and cost-effective]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-websites-are-more-resilient-and-cost-effective/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T20:04:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-websites-are-more-resilient-and-cost-effective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dave Cole, from Development Seed, wrote a
<a href="http://developmentseed.org/blog/2012/07/27/build-cms-free-websites/">comprehensive article</a>
on their journey from developing
sites with heavy-duty CMSs, through dynamic client-side pages, to &#8220;devising a process by which we build static sites
dynamically&#8221;. He explains how they leverage single-purpose web applications, existing or custom-made, to make that
easier.</p>

<p>One of the chief benefits he mentions is:</p>

<blockquote><p>We can deploy our projects on practically any web server and not worry about whether it has the right software to run our application or the technical resources to handle high traffic.</p><footer><strong>Dave Cole</strong> <cite><a href='http://developmentseed.org/blog/2012/07/27/build-cms-free-websites/'>How We Build CMS-Free Websites</a></cite></footer></blockquote>




<!-- more -->


<p>That makes sense to me and I can see this model working for many websites. This reminds me of old-school stuff
like Microsoft Frontpage&#8230; But those sites tended to be too static. Combining static content with web services and
weaving all that with client-side JavaScript can be a powerful strategy.</p>

<p>Each component does what it does best, whether it&#8217;s
serving static files (possibly through a CDN), providing single-purpose dynamic content (such as pictures, video or
comments) or implementing client-side customization and functionality.</p>

<p>This blog follows this approach: it&#8217;s built with Octopress, it&#8217;s hosted on GitHub Pages and it uses services like
Google Search, Twitter and Disqus for interactivity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static sites are worry-free]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-sites-are-worry-free/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T12:18:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-sites-are-worry-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I was reading a few more articles about the experience of using static pages instead of a dynamic engine
to host a blog or a content site. One quote caught my attention:</p>

<blockquote><p>There are no entry points to hack and there is no live webapp to go down.</p><footer><strong>Young Hahn</strong> <cite><a href='http://developmentseed.org/blog/2011/09/09/jekyll-github-pages/'>Using Jekyll and GitHub Pages for Our Site</a></cite></footer></blockquote>




<!-- more -->


<p>Static sites are worry-free. It&#8217;s a whole lot less surface area with potential
vulnerabilities. It&#8217;s one less piece of software to worry about security patches. It&#8217;s one less vector of attack.</p>

<p>For the sake of security, I don&#8217;t usually host a blog on the same server I have other stuff I care about.
But I might host a static site.</p>

<p>In this sense, using Octopress for my blog can make my life simpler.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing rbenv on Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/26/installing-rbenv-on-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T12:52:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/26/installing-rbenv-on-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I chose Octopress to publish this blog. When I was reading on how to install it, I learned that it required Ruby 1.9.2.
Octopress&#8217; documentation recommends installing it through a Ruby environment manager: either RVM or rbenv.</p>

<p>The last time I was dabbling with Ruby was a few years ago, before these tools were introduced. So I didn&#8217;t have a
favorite to pick. To choose one I
searched Google, read a little bit and came to the conclusion that rbenv is lighter and possibly simpler, while RVM
is more complex and more powerful. I&#8217;m not developing in Ruby so light and simple suits me. At the same time, RVM
messes with the builtin <code>cd</code> command and I&#8217;d rather leave it alone. So I picked rbenv.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Ubuntu has has a rbenv package, so I went for it first. I quickly had rbenv running but when I tried to install the
ruby-build rbenv plugin I couldn&#8217;t get it to work. I could have used an alternate route to install ruby-build
but I prefer the path of less resistance. I don&#8217;t like fighting the tools.</p>

<p>So I uninstalled Ubuntu&#8217;s rbenv package (which, by the way, was several versions out-of-date) and did a manual install
of rbenv from its project site.</p>

<p>These are the commands I used to install rbenv in Ubuntu 12.04 LTS (Precise Pangolin):</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3177482.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code># pre-reqs
sudo apt-get install git-core build-essential libssl-dev libreadline-dev zlib1g-dev libxml2-dev libxslt-dev

# rbenv
cd
git clone https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv.git .rbenv
echo 'export PATH=&quot;$HOME/.rbenv/bin:$PATH&quot;' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
echo 'eval &quot;$(rbenv init -)&quot;' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
exec $SHELL

# ruby-build
mkdir -p ~/.rbenv/plugins
cd ~/.rbenv/plugins
git clone https://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build.git

# install some rubies
cd
rbenv install 1.9.2-p290
rbenv install 1.9.2-p320
rbenv install 1.9.3-p194
rbenv rehash

# set a global ruby
rbenv global 1.9.2-p290</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Installing Ruby takes some time, between a large download and setup, but everything went smoothly and worked as
advertised. A great experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-25T20:43:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last few years I created a few blogs focused in different audiences:
an <a href="http://fernandoacorreia.wordpress.com/">English-language blog</a>,
a <a href="http://blogdofernandocorreia.wordpress.com/">Portuguese-language one</a>,
a blog focusing on <a href="http://plataformanuvem.wordpress.com/">cloud computing</a> and another specifically about
<a href="http://pensandoazure.wordpress.com/">Windows Azure</a>.</p>

<p>Having blogs for specific subjects or audiences has its advantages; the content is more coherent. Also there&#8217;s the
question of language: writing in Portuguese I reach people around me more easily, but writing in English I can be part
of the ongoing global exchange of information about computing.</p>

<p>But the paradox is that I found out that with so many blogs, I was writing less often.
Having posts spread all over the place makes it more difficult to manage an online presence.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After spending some time writing about a subject, it gets awkward to post in another
blog that looks abandoned. So I&#8217;ve decided to experiment with having a single, default place to write about any
subject that raises my interest at any given time.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve also decided to write mostly in English. The Brazilians that value their career in computing
know that they need to be able to read English proficiently. After all, English is the lingua franca of Computer
Science. And Google Translator is getting surprisingly accurate&#8230;</p>

<p>I&#8217;m using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to publish this blog on GitHub. There&#8217;s a lot to like about this:</p>

<ul>
<li>The blog source is text-based.</li>
<li>It uses markdown.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s stored in a git repository.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s fully versioned.</li>
<li>I have a backup of my blog on my laptop and another as a GitHub repository.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s hosted on <em>the</em> social network for programmers.</li>
<li>It has many good options for source code snippets.</li>
<li>It can handle any ammount of traffic.</li>
<li>I can use a custom domain.</li>
<li>And I have control over the blog&#8217;s structure and appearance.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
