<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Fernando Correia's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-26T20:54:14-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fernando Correia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fernandoacorreia@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing rbenv on Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/26/installing-rbenv-on-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T12:52:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/26/installing-rbenv-on-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I chose Octopress to publish this blog. When I was reading on how to install it, I learned that it required Ruby 1.9.2.
Octopress&#8217; documentation recommends installing it through a Ruby environment manager: either RVM or rbenv.</p>

<p>The last time I was dabbling with Ruby was a few years ago, before these tools were introduced. So I didn&#8217;t have a
favorite to pick. To choose one I
searched Google, read a little bit and came to the conclusion that rbenv is lighter and possibly simpler, while RVM
is more complex and more powerful. I&#8217;m not developing in Ruby so light and simple suits me. At the same time, RVM
messes with the builtin <code>cd</code> command and I&#8217;d rather leave it alone. So I picked rbenv.</p>

<p>Ubuntu has has a rbenv package, so I went for it first. I quickly had rbenv running but when I tried to install the
ruby-build rbenv plugin I couldn&#8217;t get it to work. I could have used an alternate route to install ruby-build
but I prefer the path of less resistance. I don&#8217;t like fighting the tools.</p>

<p>So I uninstalled Ubuntu&#8217;s rbenv package (which, by the way, was several versions out-of-date) and did a manual install
of rbenv from its project site.</p>

<p>These are the commands I used to install rbenv in Ubuntu 12.04 LTS (Precise Pangolin):</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3177482.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code># pre-reqs
sudo apt-get install git-core build-essential libssl-dev libreadline-dev zlib1g-dev libxml2-dev libxslt-dev

# rbenv
cd
git clone https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv.git .rbenv
echo 'export PATH=&quot;$HOME/.rbenv/bin:$PATH&quot;' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
echo 'eval &quot;$(rbenv init -)&quot;' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
exec $SHELL

# ruby-build
mkdir -p ~/.rbenv/plugins
cd ~/.rbenv/plugins
git clone https://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build.git

# install some rubies
cd
rbenv install 1.9.2-p290
rbenv install 1.9.2-p320
rbenv install 1.9.3-p194
rbenv rehash

# set a global ruby
rbenv global 1.9.2-p290</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Installing Ruby takes some time, between a large download and setup, but everything went smoothly and worked as
advertised. A great experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-25T20:43:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last few years I created a few blogs focused in different audiences:
an <a href="http://fernandoacorreia.wordpress.com/">English-language blog</a>,
a <a href="http://blogdofernandocorreia.wordpress.com/">Portuguese-language one</a>,
a blog focusing on <a href="http://plataformanuvem.wordpress.com/">cloud computing</a> and another specifically about
<a href="http://pensandoazure.wordpress.com/">Windows Azure</a>.</p>

<p>Having blogs for specific subjects or audiences has its advantages; the content is more coherent. Also there&#8217;s the
question of language: writing in Portuguese I reach people around me more easily, but writing in English I can be part
of the ongoing global exchange of information about computing.</p>

<p>But the paradox is that I found out that with so many blogs, I was writing less often.
Having posts spread all over the place makes it more difficult to
manage an online presence. After spending some time writing about a subject, it gets awkward to post in another
blog that looks abandoned.</p>

<p>So I&#8217;ve decided to experiment with having a single, default place to write about any subject that raises my interest
at any given time. I&#8217;ve also decided to write mostly in English. The Brazilians that value their career in computing
know that they need to be able to read English proficiently. After all, English is the lingua franca of Computer
Science. And Google Translator is getting surprisingly accurate&#8230;</p>

<p>I&#8217;m using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to publish this blog on GitHub. There&#8217;s a lot to like about this:</p>

<ul>
<li>The blog source is text-based.</li>
<li>It uses markdown.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s stored in a git repository.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s fully versioned.</li>
<li>I have a backup of my blog on my laptop and another as a GitHub repository.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s hosted on <em>the</em> social network for programmers.</li>
<li>It has many good options for source code snippets.</li>
<li>It can handle any ammount of traffic.</li>
<li>I can use a custom domain.</li>
<li>And I have control over the blog&#8217;s structure and appearance.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
