<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | Fernando Correia's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-10T08:40:08-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fernando Correia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fernandoacorreia@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I should pay more attention to Dojo Toolkit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/08/10/i-should-pay-more-attention-to-dojo-toolkit/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-10T08:01:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/08/10/i-should-pay-more-attention-to-dojo-toolkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been doing a lot of research on JavaScript frameworks for developing rich client-side line-of-business applications.
So far Sencha's <a href="http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs/">ExtJS</a> is the one I prefer for heavy-duty projects. But I'm constantly
looking around for alternatives and, more recently, <a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> caught my attention as a great choice
for structuring web apps.</p>

<p>Browser application technology is blooming and, recently, Steven Sanderson wrote an
<a href="http://blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/08/01/rich-javascript-applications-the-seven-frameworks-throne-of-js-2012/">excellent review</a> comparing several frameworks. There was a remarkable absence, though, as one commenter said:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>What happened to Dojo? It advocated lot of these principles years back. Was it ahead of time?</p><footer><strong>Geeth</strong> <cite><a href='http://blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/08/01/rich-javascript-applications-the-seven-frameworks-throne-of-js-2012/#comment-23446'>blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It's been many years since I last thought about Dojo. In my mind it seemed to have fallen by the wayside. But that comment
picked my interest, so I went up and updated myself on the current state of Dojo affairs.</p>

<p>I found out that not only Dojo pioneered many of the techniques being applied today in several frameworks, but it has also evolved
considerably. For instance, version 1.7 introduced an improved module system, and version 1.8 modernizes the MVC structure, among a plethora of other improvements that benefit rich client applications.</p>

<p>Dojo seems to be very mature, complete and up-to-date. It has a steeper learning curve than other, smaller approaches, though,
and historically documentation and guidance for newcomers has been lacking. By the way, this is being actively worked on as well.</p>

<p>David Walsh wrote a <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/10-reasons-why-your-projects-should-use-the-dojo-toolkit/">very interesting article</a> on what Dojo has going for it. I recommend reading it if your're interested
in JavaScript frameworks, specially for larger applications.</p>

<p>For now, I've decided to invest some time in learning Dojo and I'll be sharing my experience as I go.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Don’t start you next project without checking out all of the features Dojo has to offer!</p><footer><strong>David Walsh</strong> <cite><a href='http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/10-reasons-why-your-projects-should-use-the-dojo-toolkit/'>10 Reasons Why Your Projects Should Use the Dojo Toolkit</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
