<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: general | Fernando Correia's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-10T09:20:44-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fernando Correia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fernandoacorreia@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static websites are more resilient and cost-effective]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-websites-are-more-resilient-and-cost-effective/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T20:04:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-websites-are-more-resilient-and-cost-effective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dave Cole, from Development Seed, wrote a
<a href="http://developmentseed.org/blog/2012/07/27/build-cms-free-websites/">comprehensive article</a>
on their journey from developing
sites with heavy-duty CMSs, through dynamic client-side pages, to "devising a process by which we build static sites
dynamically". He explains how they leverage single-purpose web applications, existing or custom-made, to make that
easier.</p>

<p>One of the chief benefits he mentions is:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>We can deploy our projects on practically any web server and not worry about whether it has the right software to run our application or the technical resources to handle high traffic.</p><footer><strong>Dave Cole</strong> <cite><a href='http://developmentseed.org/blog/2012/07/27/build-cms-free-websites/'>How We Build CMS-Free Websites</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>That makes sense to me and I can see this model working for many websites. This reminds me of old-school stuff
like Microsoft Frontpage... But those sites tended to be too static. Combining static content with web services and
weaving all that with client-side JavaScript can be a powerful strategy.</p>

<p>Each component does what it does best, whether it's
serving static files (possibly through a CDN), providing single-purpose dynamic content (such as pictures, video or
comments) or implementing client-side customization and functionality.</p>

<p>This blog follows this approach: it's built with Octopress, it's hosted on GitHub Pages and it uses services like
Google Search, Twitter and Disqus for interactivity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static sites are worry-free]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-sites-are-worry-free/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T12:18:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/27/static-sites-are-worry-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I was reading a few more articles about the experience of using static pages instead of a dynamic engine
to host a blog or a content site. One quote caught my attention:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>There are no entry points to hack and there is no live webapp to go down.</p><footer><strong>Young Hahn</strong> <cite><a href='http://developmentseed.org/blog/2011/09/09/jekyll-github-pages/'>Using Jekyll and GitHub Pages for Our Site</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Static sites are worry-free. It's a whole lot less surface area with potential
vulnerabilities. It's one less piece of software to worry about security patches. It's one less vector of attack.</p>

<p>For the sake of security, I don't usually host a blog on the same server I have other stuff I care about.
But I might host a static site.</p>

<p>In this sense, using Octopress for my blog can make my life simpler.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-25T20:43:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.fernandocorreia.info/blog/2012/07/25/a-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last few years I created a few blogs focused in different audiences:
an <a href="http://fernandoacorreia.wordpress.com/">English-language blog</a>,
a <a href="http://blogdofernandocorreia.wordpress.com/">Portuguese-language one</a>,
a blog focusing on <a href="http://plataformanuvem.wordpress.com/">cloud computing</a> and another specifically about
<a href="http://pensandoazure.wordpress.com/">Windows Azure</a>.</p>

<p>Having blogs for specific subjects or audiences has its advantages; the content is more coherent. Also there's the
question of language: writing in Portuguese I reach people around me more easily, but writing in English I can be part
of the ongoing global exchange of information about computing.</p>

<p>But the paradox is that I found out that with so many blogs, I was writing less often.
Having posts spread all over the place makes it more difficult to manage an online presence.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After spending some time writing about a subject, it gets awkward to post in another
blog that looks abandoned. So I've decided to experiment with having a single, default place to write about any
subject that raises my interest at any given time.</p>

<p>I've also decided to write mostly in English. The Brazilians that value their career in computing
know that they need to be able to read English proficiently. After all, English is the lingua franca of Computer
Science. And Google Translator is getting surprisingly accurate...</p>

<p>I'm using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to publish this blog on GitHub. There's a lot to like about this:</p>

<ul>
<li>The blog source is text-based.</li>
<li>It uses markdown.</li>
<li>It's stored in a git repository.</li>
<li>It's fully versioned.</li>
<li>I have a backup of my blog on my laptop and another as a GitHub repository.</li>
<li>It's hosted on <em>the</em> social network for programmers.</li>
<li>It has many good options for source code snippets.</li>
<li>It can handle any ammount of traffic.</li>
<li>I can use a custom domain.</li>
<li>And I have control over the blog's structure and appearance.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
